jobspress.com 2008-05-09

# Nova Scotia Job and Career Listings - JobsPress.com

Privacy Policy

**INTRODUCTION**

Effective January 1, 2004, private sector organizations must follow a code for the protection of personal information in accordance with the Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act (PIPEDA). 

**CUSTOMER PERSONAL INFORMATION DEFINED**

Personal information includes any factual or subjective information about an identifiable individual. For The Chronicle Herald's purposes this includes but is not limited to name, address, telephone number, comments, transactions, credit information, Visa, MasterCard or banking information. 

Personal information does not include that which is collected for journalistic purposes or that information that may be contained in a business card, such as the name, title, business address and telephone number of an employee of an organization. 

**TEN PRINCIPLES OF FAIR INFORMATION PRACTICES**

There are ten (10) principles of fair information practices. These principles form the ground rules for the collection, use and disclosure of the personal information of our customers. As a private sector organization, we are responsible for the protection of personal information and the fair handling of that information at all times. 

The ten (10) principles that The Chronicle Herald must follow are: 

**1\. Accountability** \- The Chronicle Herald is responsible for personal information that is under its control. The individual responsible for The Chronicle Heralds compliance with respect to the principles of fair information practices is Theresa Williams, Human Resources Manager. The Chronicle Herald is responsible for personal information in its possession, including information that has been sent to a third party for processing. The Chronicle Herald shall use contractual means to provide a comparable level of protection while the information is being processed by a third party. 

**2\. Identifying Purposes** \- The Chronicle Herald shall identify the purpose for which personal information is collected at or before the time that the information is collected. 

In compliance with the Openness principle and the Individual Access principle, purposes for which personal information is collected include but are not limited to: 

  * To communicate delivery information to a newspaper carrier; 
  * To process payment of a Classified advertisement, a newspaper subscription in either hard-copy or on-line version, archived information in CD-Rom form, reprinted newspaper photographs; 
  * To communicate subscription renewal or other information to the customer.

In accordance with the Limiting Collection principle, only that information necessary to fulfill the identified purposes shall be collected. 

The identified purpose should be specified to the individual from whom the information is collected at or before the time the personal information is collected. 

This may be done orally or in writing. 

When collected personal information is to be used for a new purpose not previously identified, the new purpose shall be identified prior to use of the information. Unless the new purpose is required by law, consent of the individual is required before the information can be used for that purpose. 

Whoever is collecting the personal information should be able to explain the collection purpose to the individual from whom the information is collected. 

**3\. Consent** \- Consent and knowledge of the individual is required, except where inappropriate, for the collection, use and disclosure of their personal information. 

Except for purposes provided for in exceptions to consent, personal information may not be collected, used, or disclosed without knowledge and consent of the individual. 

A reader who enters a newspaper contest would reasonably expect that his or her relevant contact information would be collected and used to identify the reader if and when he or she was selected as a contest winner. The reader would not reasonably expect that this information would be used for a purpose other than the administration of the contest without the reader's knowledge and consent. 

A newspaper subscriber would reasonably expect that The Chronicle Herald, in addition to using the individual's name and address for mailing and billing purposes, would also contact the subscriber to solicit the renewal of his or her subscription. 

Exceptions to consent include: 

  * If it is clearly in the individuals interest and consent is not available in a timely manner; 
  * If knowledge and consent would compromise the availability or accuracy of the information and collection is required to investigate a breach of an agreement or contravention of a provincial or federal law; 
  * For journalistic, artistic or literary purposes; 
  * If the information is publicly available; 
  * To collect a debt the individual owes to The Chronicle Herald; 
  * To comply with a subpoena, warrant or court order; 
  * To a government body that suspects the information relates to national security or the conduct of international affairs or for the purpose of administering any provincial or federal law; 
  * In an emergency where an individual's life, health or security are threatened.

Consent may be obtained orally when information is collected over the telephone, in writing or in person. 

A checkoff box may be used on order forms or invoices to allow a customer to request that their personal information not be given to other organizations. Customers who do not check the box are assumed to consent to the transfer of their personal information to third parties. 

**4\. Limiting Collection** \- The Chronicle Herald will limit collection of personal information to that which is necessary for the purpose of collection and shall do so using fair and lawful means. 

The Chronicle Herald shall not collect personal information indiscriminately. The Chronicle Herald will not deceive or mislead customers about the reasons for collecting their personal information. 

The amount and type of information gathered will be limited to that which is necessary in order to fulfill the identified purpose. 

**5\. Limiting Use, Disclosure and Retention** \- The Chronicle Herald shall not use or disclose personal information for any purpose other than that for which the information was collected unless consent is provided by the customer or the use or disclosure is authorized by the Act. 

**USE OF PERSONAL INFORMATION**

The information shall not be used for purposes other than those made known at the time of collection of the personal information. Personal information that has been collected during the course of past activities does not need to be recollected. In order to continue to use or disclose it, however, consent is required. Customers must be notified about what is done with their information, to whom it is disclosed and they must be given the option to object to these ongoing uses or disclosures. 

**DISCLOSURE OF PERSONAL INFORMATION**

Personal information may be disclosed only for the purpose for which it was collected. 

The Chronicle Herald may disclose the contact information of their customers to a third party for the following purposes: 

  * To facilitate newspaper delivery; 
  * To encourage subscription renewal; 
  * To prepare bulk mailings of information to customers pertinent to their newspaper delivery or newspaper subscription; 
  * To third party service providers communicating with customers, on behalf of The Chronicle Herald, regarding their subscription account status.

Such third parties shall be contractually bound to protect this personal contact information in accordance with the policies and procedures of The Chronicle Herald. 

The Chronicle Herald will not sell, lease or trade the personal information of their customers to third parties unless express consent is obtained from the customer. 

**RETENTION OF PERSONAL INFORMATION** A customer is no longer a customer seven years past their most recent business transaction and their personal information will be destroyed in accordance with the Safeguards principle. 

**6\. Accuracy** \- The Chronicle Herald will keep personal information as accurate, complete and up-to-date as is necessary and will take into account its use and the interests of the customer. 

Personal information will not be routinely updated and will be updated only when necessary in order to fulfill the identified purpose or upon request by the customer. 

Unless there are clearly set out limits, frequently used information will be kept as accurate and up-to-date as is necessary for the identified purpose. 

**7\. Safeguards** Personal information of customers shall be protected regardless of its format. The Chronicle Herald shall safeguard the information from unauthorized access, disclosure, copying, modification, loss or theft. 

If necessary to transport personal information, it shall be contained in a sealed envelope and transported personally. Interoffice mail distribution is not acceptable. 

Credit cardholder data received by regular mail shall be processed in a restricted area and only authorized staff may access this data. 

Credit cardholder data may be received by fax machine to a fax machine located in a restricted area with limited authorized access. Authorized staff must be accountable for all documents containing cardholder information. 

Telephone orders that include credit card payment are permitted; however, telephone representatives must not record the credit cardholder information in any form other than that necessary to process the payment. If recorded in hardcopy form, the form must be appropriately destroyed upon processing of the payment. 

Personal information shall be stored in locked cabinets or password protected electronic files at all times unless it is being used for an identifiable purpose. 

No personal information shall be left unattended at any time that it is not contained within a locked cabinet or password protected electronic file. 

Personal information may be kept only as long as necessary to satisfy the purpose for which it was collected. 

All hard-copy reports or documents containing customer information shall identify the customer only by an account number. 

**DESTRUCTION OF PERSONAL INFORMATION**

All hard-copy forms, records, papers or other document containing personal information shall be shredded once the information is no longer required for an identified purpose. 

All computerized records containing personal information shall be purged once the information is no longer required for an identified purpose. 

**ACCESS TO PERSONAL INFORMATION**

Access to customer personal information is on a "need-to-know" basis only. Personal information that has no relevance to the transaction is to be masked or removed when copies of information is provided to others. 

8\. Openness - The Chronicle Herald shall make its privacy policy understandable and easily available to its customers. 

The following information will be readily available on thechronicleherald.ca website: 

  * The name, title and address of The Chronicle Herald's privacy compliance officer; 
  * A copy of The Chronicle Herald's Privacy Policy; 
  * The name, title and address of the person to whom access to information requests should be sent; 
  * The procedure for a customer to gain access to their personal information; 
  * A description of that personal information which is made available to third parties and the purpose for which it is disclosed.

**9\. Individual Access** \- Upon request, the customer shall be informed of any personal information we have about them as well as its use and disclosure. An opportunity shall be extended to correct or amend any personal information if its accuracy and completeness is challenged or incorrect. 

Except when The Chronicle Herald is required by law to not disclose personal information to the individual, should a customer request a copy of their personal information, the request shall be complied with within thirty days. The 30-day response time limit may be extended if: responding to the request within the original 30 days would unreasonably interfere with The Chronicle Herald's business activities; if additional time is necessary to convert the personal information to an alternate format; or, if additional time is necessary to conduct consultations. If an extension to the original 30 days is required, The Chronicle Herald will notify the customer of their right to complain to the Privacy Commissioner of Canada. 

Access to a customer's personal information shall be provided at minimal or no cost. If cost is necessary, the customer will be advised of the approximate cost prior to processing the request. 

In order to ensure that information within a customer record is easily understood, any acronym, abbreviation or code used within the customer's personal information shall be explained to the customer. 

Where appropriate, amended customer information will be forwarded to any third party that has access to the information. 

If it is necessary to refuse access, the customer will be informed in writing and will be advised of reasons and any possible recourse. 

The Chronicle Herald must refuse access to personal information in the following circumstances: 

  * If it would reveal personal information about another individual that cannot be removed unless consent is provided by the other individual or if a life-threatening situation exists; 
  * If The Chronicle Herald had disclosed information to a government body for law enforcement or national security reasons and that body has instructed The Chronicle Herald to refuse access or to not reveal that the information has been released; 
  * Solicitor-client privilege; 
  * If it was collected without the individuals knowledge or consent to ensure its availability and accuracy and the collection was required to investigate a breach of an agreement or contravention of a provincial or federal law; 
  * If the information was generated in the course of a formal dispute resolution process.

**10\. Challenging Compliance** \- A customer may address a challenge concerning compliance with the principles of the Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act (PIPEDA) to The Chronicle Heralds privacy compliance officer. 

The customer shall be made aware of The Chronicle Herald's Privacy Policy and that it is in place for protection of their personal information. The customer shall be offered a copy of this policy. 

The customer shall be provided with the name, title and address of the person accountable for The Chronicle Heralds privacy policies and practices. This person is presently Theresa Williams, Human Resources Manager, The Chronicle Herald, P O Box 610, Halifax, NS, B3J 2T2. Phone: (902)426-1103, Fax: (902)426-0449, Email: [twilliams@herald.ca](mailto:twilliams@herald.ca). 

All complaints shall be investigated and the customer will be advised of the outcome. If a complaint is justified, The Chronicle Herald shall take appropriate steps to resolve the complaint including but not limited to amendment of The Chronicle Heralds policies and procedures. 

In the event the complaint is not resolved to the customer's satisfaction, the customer may have recourse to additional remedies through the Office of the Privacy Commissioner of Canada, 112 Kent Street, Place de Ville, Tower B, 3rd Floor, Ottawa, Ontario, K1A 1H3, or toll-free at 1.800.282.1376, [www.privcom.gc.ca](http://www.privcom.gc.ca/).
